Hi everybody. So my name is Mac.
مرحباً بالجميع. اسمي "ماك".
My job is that I lie to children,
عملي هو الكذب على الأطفال،
but they're honest lies.
و لكنها كذبات بيضاء.
I write children's books,
أُؤلف كتب للأطفال،
and there's a quote from Pablo Picasso,
و هناك اقتباس من "بابلو بيكاسو"،
"We all know that Art is not truth.
"نعلم جميعاً بأن الفن ليس صدقاً.
or at least the truth that is given us to understand.
أو على الأقل الحقيقة التي تُعطى لنا لنفهم.
The artist must know the manner whereby
على الفنان أن يعلم الطريقة بحيث
to convince others of the truthfulness of his lies."
يُقنع الآخرين بصدق كذباته."
I first heard this when I was a kid,
لقد سَمِعْت هذا وانا طفل.
and I loved it,
ولقد أعجبتني،
but I had no idea what it meant.
ولكن ليس عندي أدنى فكرة عن المراد منها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I thought, you know what, it's what I'm here
اعتقد أنكم عرفتم لماذا انا هنا
to talk to you today about, though,
لأتحدث معكم اليوم عن،
truth and lies, fiction and reality.
الصدق والكذب، الخيال والحقيقة.
So how could I untangle
لذلك كيف احل هذه
this knotted bunch of sentences?
مجموعة الجمل المعقدة؟
And I said, I've got PowerPoint. Let's do a Venn diagram.
وَقُلْت، لدي برنامج عرض تقديمي. لنقوم بمقارنه.
["Truth. Lies."] (Laughter)
["الصدق. الكذب"] (ضحك)
So there it is, right there, boom.
انظروا إليه،
We've got truth and lies
لدينا الصدق والكذب
and then there's this little space,
هناك فراغ بسيط.
the edge, in the middle.
الحافة، التي في المنتصف.
That liminal space, that's art.
الفراغ المحدود، انه الفن.
All right. Venn diagram. (Laughter) (Applause)
حسناً. الرسم البياني. (ضحك) (تصفيق)
But that's actually not very helpful either.
ولكن هذا لا يساعد أيضآ.
The thing that made me understand
والشيء الذي جعلني افهم
that quote and really kind of what art,
هذا الاقتباس وفهم ما هو الفن،
at least the art of fiction, was,
او على الأقل فن الخيال،
was working with kids.
هو العمل مع الأطفال.
I used to be a summer camp counselor.
كُنت أعمل كمستشار للمخيمات الصيفية.
I would do it on my summers off from college,
اعمل في عُطَل الصيف اثناء دراستي الجامعية،
and I loved it.
ولقد أعجبتني.
It was a sports summer camp
لقد كان مخيماََ صيفيّا رياضياََ
for four- to six-year-olds.
للأطفال بين عمر الرابعة والسادسة
I was in charge of the four-year-olds,
كُنت مسؤولاََ عن الأطفال الذين بعمر الرابعة،
which is good, because
وهنا جيد، لأنهم
four-year-olds can't play sports, and neither can I.
لا يستطيعون ممارسة الرياضة، ولا حتى انا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I play sports at a four-year-old level,
لعبت رياضة مناسبة لسن الرابعة،
so what would happen is the kids would
لذلك ما الذي حَصل هو ان الأطفال
dribble around some cones, and then got hot,
يلعب حول بعض الأعمدة، وبعد ان يشعروا بالحر،
and then they would go sit underneath the tree
يتجهون لشل الشجرة ويجلسون تحتها
where I was already sitting — (Laughter) —
وانا كنت جالس من قبل- (ضحك) -
and I would tell them stories about my life.
احكي لهم قصة حياتي.
I would tell them about how, on the weekends,
احكي لهم، في عطل نهاية الأسبوع،
I would go home and I would spy for the Queen of England.
اني اذهب لمنزلي ثم أتحسس على ملكة إنجلترا.
And soon, other kids
وبعد فترة، الأطفال الآخرون
who weren't even in my group of kids,
والذين لم يكونوا في مجموعتي،
they would come up to me, and they would say,
جاؤوا لي، ثم قالوا ،
"You're Mac Barnett, right?
"أنت ماك بارنيت، صح؟
You're the guy who spies for the Queen of England."
انت الذي تتجسس على ملكة انجلترا."
And I had been waiting my whole life for strangers
وكنت انتظر طوال حياتي الغرباء
to come up and ask me that question.
ان يأتوني ليسألوني هذا السؤال.
In my fantasy, they were svelte Russian women,
في عالم الخيالي، كُنَ نساء روسيات جميلات،
but, you know, four-year-olds —
لكن كما تعرفون ، أنهم في الرابعة
you take what you can get in Berkeley, California.
تاخذ ما تستطيع الحصول عليه من بيركلي كاليفورنيا.
And I realized that the stories that I was telling
ولاحظت ان القصص التي احكيها
were real in this way that was familiar to me
كانت حقيقة بالنسبة لي بطريقة ما
and really exciting.
وشيقة جداً.
I think the pinnacle of this for me — I'll never forget this —
اظن ان قمة هذا الشيء -انني لن أنسها-
there was this little girl named Riley. She was tiny,
كانت من بينهم طفلة هزيلة تدعى رايلي
and she used to always take out her lunch every day
وكانت تُخرج غداءها كل يوم
and she would throw out her fruit.
ومن ثم ترمي بالفاكهة،
She would just take her fruit,
كانت تأتي بالفاكهة معها،
her mom packed her a melon every day,
وكانت انها تعطيها الشمام كل يوم،
and she would just throw it in the ivy
فترمي الفتاة به في العُشب
and then she would eat fruit snacks
ومن ثم تاكل وجبة فواكه خفيفة
and pudding cups, and I was like, "Riley,
مع أكواب من الحلوى، فأقول لها"رايلي،
you can't do that, you have to eat the fruit."
لا يمكنكِ عمل هذا،، يجب ان تآكلي الفاكهة."
And she was like, "Why?"
وتسأل، "لماذا"
And I was like, "Well, when you throw the fruit in the ivy,
فأقول، "انتي رميت الفاكهة بالعشب،
pretty soon, it's going to be overgrown with melons,"
في القريب العاجل، سيذهب مع الشمام داخل الارض مع الشمام."
which is why I think I ended up
والذي جعلني انتهي الى
telling stories to children and not being a nutritionist for children.
ان احكي القصص للاطفال ولا أبقى أخصائي أغذية.
And so Riley was like, "That will never happen.
فلذلك قررت رايلي ان لا تفعلها ابداَْ.
That's not going to happen."
لن افعلها مرة اخرى."
And so, on the last day of camp,
لذلك كان اخر يوم من المخيم،
I got up early and I got a big cantaloupe
استيقظت باكراً وحصلت على شمام ضخم
from the grocery store
من البقالة
and I hid it in the ivy,
وأخفيتها في العشب،
and then at lunchtime, I was like,
وعندما حان موعد الغداء،قلت
"Riley, why don't you go over there and see what you've done."
"رايلي، لمذا لا تذهبين هناك، وترين ماذا فعلته."
And — (Laughter) —
و (ضحك)
she went trudging through the ivy, and then her eyes
ومشيت ببطئ، وبدت عينيها
just got so wide, and she pointed out this melon
واسعتين واشارت للشمام
that was bigger than her head,
إنه اكبر من رأسها،
and then all the kids ran over there and rushed around her,
وركض الأطفال إليها، وأحاطوا بها،
and one of the kids was like, "Hey,
احدهم قال لها، "أوه،
why is there a sticker on this?"
لماذا يوجد لاصق الشمام؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was like, "That is also why I say
ثم قلت، "هذا هو السبب في قولي
do not throw your stickers in the ivy.
لا ترموا اللواصق بالعشب.
Put them in the trash can. It ruins nature when you do this."
ضعوها بالقمامة. إنها تفسد الطبيعة عندما تفعلوا ذلك."
And Riley carried that melon around with her all day,
ودارت رايلي بالشمام معها طوال اليوم،
and she was so proud.
وكانت فخورة جداً.
And Riley knew she didn't grow a melon in seven days,
وعَلِمت رايلي انها لم تعتني بالشمام طوال السبع الأيام،
but she also knew that she did,
ولكنها عَلِمت انها فعلته،
and it's a weird place,
انه مكان غريب،
but it's not just a place that kids can get to.
إنه ليس مكان للأطفال ليذهبوا اليه.
It's anything. Art can get us to that place.
إنه اي شيء. الفن يمكنه جلب ذلك المكان لنا.
She was right in that place in the middle,
لقد كانت محقةََ في ذلك منتصف ذلك المكان،
that place which you could call art or fiction.
المكان الذي يُمكن ان نطلق عليه فن او خيال.
I'm going to call it wonder.
سأطلق عليه التأمل.
It's what Coleridge called the willing suspension of disbelief
إنه كما يطلق عليه كوليردج رغبة إيقاف الكفر
or poetic faith,
أو الإيمان الشاعري،
for those moments where a story, no matter how strange,
بالنسبة لهم هذه القصة، مهما كانت غريبة،
has some semblance of the truth,
لها شكل من أشكال الحقيقة،
and then you're able to believe it.
ولذلك يمكنك تصديقها.
It's not just kids who can get there.
ليس الأطفال هم من يصدقها فقط.
Adults can too, and we get there when we read.
البالغون كذلك، عندما نقرأها.
It's why in two days, people will be
ولذلك خلال يومين، الناس سوف
descending on Dublin to take the walking tour
سينالون لدبلن للقيام بجولة
of Bloomsday and see everything that happened in "Ulysses,"
في يوم مزدهر لرؤية ما حدث في "يوليسيس،"
even though none of that happened.
حتى لو لم يحصل من ذلك شيء.
Or people go to London and they visit Baker Street
او يزور الناس شارع الخبازين في لندن
to see Sherlock Holmes' apartment,
لمشاهدة شقة شارلوك هولز،
even though 221B is just a number that was painted
حتى لو كان B211 مجرد رقم مكتوب
on a building that never actually had that address.
على عمارة لا يوجد لها عنوان.
We know these characters aren't real,
نعلم كلنا ان الشخصيات غير حقيقية،
but we have real feelings about them,
ولكننا نشعر داخلياََ بهم،
and we're able to do that.
ونستطيع ان نفعل ذلك.
We know these characters aren't real,
نعلم ان هذه الشخصيات غير حقيقة.
and yet we also know that they are.
وبعد ذلك ايضاََ نعلم انهم كذلك.
Kids can get there a lot more easily than adults can,
الأطفال يصلون الى ذلك بسهولة اكثر من البالغين.
and that's why I love writing for kids.
ولهذا السبب أحب ان اكتب للاطفال.
I think kids are the best audience
أرىان الأطفال هم افضل جمهور
for serious literary fiction.
لأعمال الأدب الخيالي.
When I was a kid,
عندما كنت طفلا،
I was obsessed with secret door novels,
كنت مهووساََ بروايات الباب السري،
things like "Narnia,"
مثل "نارينا،"
where you would open a wardrobe and go through to a magical land.
عندما تفتح باب خزانة الملابس ثم تدخل الى الارض السحرية.
And I was convinced that secret doors really did exist
وكنت مقتنعاً بوجود هذا الباب
and I would look for them and try to go through them.
وحاولت مرارا البحث عنه لدخوله.
I wanted to live and cross over into that fictional world, which is —
تمنيت ان أعيش في العالم الخيالي،
I would always just open people's closet doors. (Laughter)
اريد فقط ان افتح خزانات ملابس الناس.
I would just go through my mom's boyfriend's closet,
حتى خزانة صديق أمي،
and there was not a secret magical land there.
ولم تكن هناك ارض سرية سحرية.
There was some other weird stuff that I think my mom should know about.
إنما يوجد أشياء غربية على أمي معرفتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was happy to tell her all about it.
وكنت سعيدا عندما اخبرها بذلك.
After college, my first job was working
وبعد التخرج، كان أول عمل لي
behind one of these secret doors.
خلف احد هذه الأبواب السرية.
This is a place called 826 Valencia.
يطلق على هذا المكان 826 ڤالينسيا.
It's at 826 Valencia Street
في شارع ڤالينسيا 826
in the Mission in San Francisco,
في ماشين في سان فرانسيسكو،
and when I worked there, there was a publishing company
وعندما عملت هناك، كان بجانبنا مطبعة
headquartered there called McSweeney's,
ومقرها الرئيسي هو مكسويني
a nonprofit writing center called 826 Valencia,
مركز للكتابة غير تجاري اسمه ڤالينسيا 826
but then the front of it
ولكن بأمامه
was a strange shop.
محل غريب.
You see, this place was zoned retail,
كما ترون، إنه محل بيع مفرق،
and in San Francisco, they were not going to give us a variance,
ولن يعطونا في سان فرانسيسكو اي فرق،
and so the writer who founded it, a writer named Dave Eggers,
أنشأه الكاتب دايفيد ايقرز،
to come into compliance with code, he said, "Fine,
وليدخل حيّز التنفيذ مع القانون، قال،"حسناََ،
I'm just going to build a pirate supply store."
سابني محل مؤن للقراصنة."
And that's what he did. (Laughter)
وهذا ما فعله. (ضحك)
And it's beautiful. It's all wood.
إنه جميل. كل شيء من الخشب.
There's drawers you can pull out and get citrus
يوجد درج يمكنك فتحه والحصول على حمضيات
so you don't get scurvy.
لذلك لا تكن دنيء.
They have eyepatches in lots of colors,
لديهم غطاء للعين (كالقرصان) بألوان مختلفه،
because when it's springtime, pirates want to go wild.
لانه وقت الربيع، فالقراصنة يريدون المغامرة.
You don't know. Black is boring. Pastel.
لا تعرف . الأسود اصبح مملاََ. ألوان.
Or eyes, also in lots of colors,
أو أفيون، بألوان مختلفة،
just glass eyes, depending on how you want
نظارات، تعتمد على رغبتك
to deal with that situation.
في التعامل مع الموقف.
And the store, strangely,
والمحل، بغرابة،
people came to them and bought things,
تأتي الناس إِليه لشراء الأشياء،
and they ended up paying the rent
وينتهي بهم المطاف لاستأجر
for our tutoring center, which was behind it,
مركز الإرشاد، والذي كان بخلفه،
but to me, more important was the fact
لكن بالنسبة لي، كان الأهم هو حقيقة
that I think the quality of work you do,
ان قيمة عملك الذي تعمل،
kids would come and get instruction in writing,
ان الاطفال يأتون للتوجيه في الكتابة،
and when you have to walk this weird, liminal, fictional space like this to go do your writing,
وعندما تضطر للمشي بغرابة، للحدود، الفضاء الخيالي كهذا
it's going to affect the kind of work that you make.
سيأمر على عملك الذي تقوم به.
It's a secret door that you can walk through.
إنه الباب السري الذي يمكنك دخوله.
So I ran the 826 in Los Angeles,
لذلك أدرت 826 في لوس انجلوس،
and it was my job to build the store down there.
وكان عملي هو بناء محل هناك.
So we have The Echo Park Time Travel Mart.
لدينا سوق حديقة صدى السفر عبر الزمن.
That's our motto: "Whenever you are, we're already then."
هذا شعارنا "حيثما كنت، نحن مستعدون."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it's on Sunset Boulevard in Los Angeles.
إنه في شارع الغروب في لوس أنجلس.
Our friendly staff is ready to help you.
طاقمنا الطيب مستعدون لمساعدتك.
They're from all eras,
إنهم من كل زمن،
including just the 1980s, that guy on the end,
حتى في زمن الثمانينيّات، الشخص في النهايةً،
he's from the very recent past.
إنه من اخر الماضي.
There's our Employees of the Month,
هؤلاء موظفو الشهر،
including Genghis Khan, Charles Dickens.
من ضمنهم جنكيزخان ، وتشارلز دوكنز.
Some great people have come up through our ranks.
بعض العضماء في قائمتنا.
This is our kind of pharmacy section.
هذا قسم الصيدلية.
We have some patent medicines,
لدينا بعض المرضى،
Canopic jars for your organs,
جرة لاعضائك،
communist soap that says,
صابون شيوعي كما يقال،
"This is your soap for the year." (Laughter)
"هذا صابون السنة." (ضحك)
Our slushy machine broke
آلة العصير متعطلة
on the opening night and we didn't know what to do.
في الليلة المفتوحة وليس باستطاعتنا عمل شيء.
Our architect was covered in red syrup.
مهندسان كان مغطى بِالشَّرَاب الأحمر.
It looked like he had just murdered somebody,
كأنه ارتكب جريمة قتل.
which it was not out of the question
والتي لم تكن خارج السؤال
for this particular architect,
بالنسبة لهذا المهندس،
and we didn't know what to do.
ولم نكن نعرف ما الذي نعمله.
It was going to be the highlight of our store.
كانت ستكون العلامة الفارقة لمحلنا.
So we just put that sign on it that said,
لذلك وضعنا علامة تقول،
"Out of order. Come back yesterday." (Laughter)
"لا تعمل . تعال أمس." (ضحك)
And that ended up being a better joke than slushies,
والذي انتهى بِنَا الى أفضل طرفة من العصير،
so we just left it there forever.
لذلك تركناها للأبد.
Mammoth Chunks. These things weigh, like, seven pounds each.
قطع المامو. هذه الأشياء وزن 7 أرطال للقطعة.
Barbarian repellent. It's full of salad
طارد البرابرة. إنه مليء بالسلطة
and potpourri — things that barbarians hate.
والمجففات- أشياء يكرهها البرابرة.
Dead languages.
اللغات الميتة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Leeches, nature's tiny doctors.
الدود، الطبيب الصغير الطبيعي.
And Viking Odorant, which comes in lots of great scents:
ورائحة الفايكنغ، والتي تأتي من كثير من الروائح الطيبة:
toenails, sweat and rotten vegetables, pyre ash.
كأظفار القدم، والخضار الطيبة والمتعفنة، ورماد محرقة الجثث.
Because we believe that Axe Body Spray
لأننا نعتقد أن بخاخ فأس الجسم
is something that you should only find on the battlefield,
هو شيء ينبغي عليك إيجاده في ساحة القتال،
not under your arms. (Laughter)
وليس في إبطيك. (ضحك)
And these are robot emotion chips,
وهذه شرائح لمشاعر للإنسان الآلي،
so robots can feel love or fear.
فالإنسان الآلي يستطيع الشعور بالحب أو الخوف.
Our biggest seller is Schadenfreude,
أكبر مبيعاتنا هو الشماتة،
which we did not expect.
والتي لم نكن نتوقعها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We did not think that was going to happen.
لم نكن نظن ان يحدث هذا.
But there's a nonprofit behind it,
لكن خلفها مركز غير ربحي ،
and kids go through a door that says "Employees Only"
والأطفال يدخلون باباََ مكتوب عليه "للموظفين فقط"
and they end up in this space
وينتهي بهم المطاف في هذه الساحة
where they do homework and write stories
والتي يؤدون فيها واجباتهم ويكتبون قصصهم
and make films and this is a book release party
وتصوير فيلم، وهذا كتاب تم طبعه، وهذا حفلٌ
where kids will read.
والتي يقرأ من خلالها الاطفال.
There's a quarterly that's published
كل ربع سنة يتم طبع
with just writing that's done by the kids
ما تَم كتابته من قبل الاطفال
who come every day after school,
والذين يأتون بعد المدرسة كل يوم،
and we have release parties
وأقمنا حفلات
and they eat cake and read for their parents
وأكلوا الكيك وقرؤوا لوالديهم
and drink milk out of champagne glasses.
وشربوا الحليب من كؤوس الشامبانيا.
And it's a very special space,
وإنها مساحة خاصة جداََ،
because it's this weird space in the front.
لأنها ساحة غريبة في المقدمة.
The joke isn't a joke.
الطرفة ليست طرفة.
You can't find the seams on the fiction,
لا تستطيع أن تجد الخطوط في الخيال،
and I love that. It's this little bit of fiction
والتي أحبها. إنه قليل من الخيال
that's colonized the real world.
هذه المستعمرة هي العالم الحقيقي.
I see it as kind of a book in three dimensions.
انا ارها كنوع من الكتب الثلاثية الابعاد.
There's a term called metafiction,
هذا الفريق يسمى الميتافكشن،
and that's just stories about stories,
وهو القصص عن القِصص،
and meta's having a moment now.
والميتا يمتلك لحظة الان.
Its last big moment was probably in the 1960s
إن آخر لاحظتها الكبيرة هي من المحتمل في الستينات
with novelists like John Barth and William Gaddis,
مع الروائيين مثل جون بارث وولائم قادس،
but it's been around.
لكن كانت قريبة.
It's almost as old as storytelling itself.
إنها قديمة كرواية القصص.
And one metafictive technique
وأاحد تقنية ميتافكتيف
is breaking the fourth wall. Right?
هو كسر الجدران الأربعة. صحيح؟
It's when an actor will turn to the audience
وهي عندما يلتفت الممثل إلى الجمهور
and say, "I am an actor,
ويقول،"أنا الممثل،
these are just rafters."
وهؤلاء فقط العوارض."
And even that supposedly honest moment,
وبالرغم من كونها لحظة صادقة،
I would argue, is in service of the lie,
سأجادل، إنها في خدمة الكذب،
but it's supposed to foreground the artificiality
ولكن من المفترض أن تصنع المقدمة
of the fiction.
في الخيال.
For me, I kind of prefer the opposite.
بالنسبة لي، أُفضل العكس.
If I'm going to break down the fourth wall,
وإن قمت بإسقاط الجدار الأربعة،
I want fiction to escape
اريد الخيال ان يهرب
and come into the real world.
ويأتي للعالم الجديد.
I want a book to be a secret door that opens
أريد باب سري بالكتاب يُفتح
and lets the stories out into reality.
وأدع القصص تخرج للواقع.
And so I try to do this in my books.
لذلك أحاول تطبيقها بكتبي.
And here's just one example.
وهذا إحدى الأمثلة.
This is the first book that I ever made.
هذا اول كتاب ألفته.
It's called "Billy Twitters and his Blue Whale Problem."
اسمه "بايلي المغرد ومشكلة حوته الأزرق."
And it's about a kid who gets a blue whale as a pet
إنها عن طفل حصل على حوت ازرق أليف
but it's a punishment
لكنها عقوبة
and it ruins his life.
وأفسدت حياته.
So it's delivered overnight by FedUp.
لذلك تم تسليمها في الليل من فيداب = الساخط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he has to take it to school with him.
وهو ملزم بأخذه للمدرسة معه.
He lives in San Francisco —
يعيش في سان فرانسيسكو-
very tough city to own a blue whale in.
مدينة قاسية جداََ لتملك حوت أزرق بها.
A lot of hills, real estate is at a premium.
الكثير من التلال، العقارات مرتفعة .
This market's crazy, everybody.
هذا السوق مجنون، كل شخص.
But underneath the jacket is this case,
ولكن القضية تحت السترة،
and that's the cover underneath the book, the jacket,
وهذا الغطاء أسفل الكتاب، السترة،
and there's an ad
وهذه الدعاية
that offers a free 30-day risk-free trial
والتي توفر تجربة 30 يوم مجانية
for a blue whale.
للحوت الازرق.
And you can just send in a self-addressed stamped envelope
ويمكنك إرسال رسالة ذاتية مختومة ومغلفة
and we'll send you a whale.
وسنرسل لك حوت.
And kids do write in.
والأطفال كتبوا بداخله.
So here's a letter. It says, "Dear people,
والآن هنا رسالة. تقول،"أعزائي الناس،
I bet you 10 bucks you won't send me a blue whale.
أراهنك بعشر دولارات، أنك لن ترسل حوتاََ ازرق
Eliot Gannon (age 6)."
إليوت غانون ست سنوات."
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So what Eliot and the other kids
لذلك ما الذي إليوت والأطفال الاخرين
who send these in get back
الذين ارسلوا حصلوا عليه
is a letter in very small print from a Norwegian law firm —
إنه رسالة صغير مطبوعة من شركة قانون نرويجيه
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
that says that due to a change in customs laws,
والتي تقول بسبب التغير في قانون الزبائن،
their whale has been held up in Sognefjord,
تم احتجاز حوتهم في سقنو،
which is a very lovely fjord,
والذي هو مضيق رائع جداًَ،
and then it just kind of talks about Sognefjord
إنه فقط كلام فقط عن مضيق سقنو
and Norwegian food for a little while. It digresses.
والطعام النرويجي لمدة بسيطة. إنه مقزز.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it finishes off by saying that
ولكن انتهت بالقول
your whale would love to hear from you.
حوتك يرغب أن يسمع منك.
He's got a phone number,
فعنده رقم هاتف،
and you can call and leave him a message.
يمكنك الاتصال به وترك رسالة له إن احببت،
And when you call and leave him a message,
وعندما تفعل ذلك،
you just, on the outgoing message,
ستكون في الرسائل الصادرة،
it's just whale sounds and then a beep,
إنه فقط صوت الحوت ورنة بعدها،
which actually sounds a lot like a whale sound.
والتي بالمناسبة قريبة من صوت الحوت.
And they get a picture of their whale too.
وعندهم صورة للحوت.
So this is Randolph,
هذا راندولف
and Randolph belongs to a kid named Nico
وراندلوف ينتمي لطفل يدعى نيكو
who was one of the first kids to ever call in,
وهو اول طفل من نوعه يسمى بذلك،
and I'll play you some of Nico's message.
وسأشغل لكم بعض رسالة نيكو.
This is the first message I ever got from Nico.
هذه اول رسالة من نيكو.
(Audio) Nico: Hello, this is Nico.
(تسجيل) نيكو: اهلًا:، أنا نيكو.
I am your owner, Randolph. Hello.
إنَّا مالكك، يا راندلوف. مرحباً.
So this is the first time I can ever talk to you,
هذه المرة الاولى التي اتحدث إليك،
and I might talk to you soon another day. Bye.
وربما اتحدث إليك قريبا. مع السلامة.
Mac Barnett: So Nico called back, like, an hour later.
ماك بارنيت: والآن نيكو أعاد الاتصال بعد ساعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And here's another one of Nico's messages.
والآن رسالة اخرى من رسائل نيكو.
(Audio) Nico: Hello, Randolph, this is Nico.
(تسجيل) نيكو: اهلًا، راندلوف. أنا نيكو.
I haven't talked to you for a long time,
لم اتحدث إليك منذ زمن بعيد،
but I talked to you on Saturday or Sunday,
لكن تحدثت معك يوم السبت او الأحد،
yeah, Saturday or Sunday,
نعم، السبت او الأحد،
so now I'm calling you again
والآن اتصلت عليك مرة أخرى
to say hello and I wonder what you're doing right now,
للسلام عليك، وسؤالك ماذا تعمل الان،
and I'm going to probably call you again
وسأتصل عليك مرة أخرى محتمل
tomorrow or today,
غداً أو اليوم،
so I'll talk to you later. Bye.
لذلك سأتصل عليك لاحقاََ. مع السلامة.
MB: So he did, he called back that day again.
المتحدث: بالفعل اتصل مرة اخر ذلك اليوم.
He's left over 25 messages for Randolph
لقد ترك 25 رسالة لراندلوف
over four years.
خلال أربع سنوات.
You find out all about him
ستجد كل شيء عنه
and the grandma that he loves
وجدته التي يحبها
and the grandma that he likes a little bit less —
وجدته الاخرى التي يحبها بشكل اقل
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)
and the crossword puzzles that he does,
والكلمات المتقاطعة التي يحلها.
and this is — I'll play you one more message from Nico.
والآن سأستغل لكم رسالة أخرى من نيكو.
This is the Christmas message from Nico.
هذه رسالة عيد الميلاد من نيكو.
[Beep] (Audio) Nico: Hello, Randolph,
[ رنة] (تسجيل) نيكو: أهلا، راندلوف
sorry I haven't talked to you in a long time.
أنا أسف فلم اتحدث معك منذ فترة طويلة.
It's just that I've been so busy
أنا كنت مشغول جداََ
because school started,
لأن المدرسة بدأت.
as you might not know, probably,
كما انك من المحتمل لا تعرف،
since you're a whale, you don't know,
لأنك حوت، فلا تعرف،
and I'm calling you to just say,
وأنا اتصلت عليك لاقول لك
to wish you a merry Christmas.
عيد ميلاد سعيد.
So have a nice Christmas,
لذلك استمتع بالعيد،
and bye-bye, Randolph. Goodbye.
مع السلامة راندولف. مع السلامة.
MB: I actually got Nico,
المتحدث: أنا افهم نيكو،
I hadn't heard from in 18 months,
لم اسمع منه منذ 18شهراََ،
and he just left a message two days ago.
ولكنه ترك رسالة منذ يومين.
His voice is completely different,
صوته تغير تماماً،
but he put his babysitter on the phone,
لكنه جعل المربية تتحدث،
and she was very nice to Randolph as well.
وكانت طيبة جداََ مع راندلوف كذلك.
But Nico's the best reader I could hope for.
لكن نيكو افضل قارئ كما أرجو.
I would want anyone I was writing for
أتمنى من اي شخص اكتب له
to be in that place emotionally
أن يكون عاطفي في هذا المكان
with the things that I create.
مع الأشياء التي اخترعتها.
I feel lucky. Kids like Nico are the best readers,
اشعر بالحظ. الاطفال امثال نيكو أفضل قراء،
and they deserve the best stories we can give them.
ويستحقون أفضل ما نستطيع ان نكتب من القصص.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(ضحك)